I'm in a Daze
as I Have No Dreams in Life
(Questioner) You make
a lot of choices throughout life.
(Questioner) I wonder
how you make up your mind
when making choices
among many options.
Your question is too vague.
I wanted to pee,
so I chose to go to the restroom.
I received an urgent phone call
from Bangkok.
I had to take the call,
say hello to a Mr. Kang, the congressman,
and come to this lecture on time.
If I had more time,
I could've done all three.
But everything happened at once,
I had to do all.
So I made a choice to give up the call.
The person who called me
had to board a plane soon,
so couldn't reschedule the call.
So we gave up talking.
I met the congressman
on my way to this lecture.
On my way I had to pee,
so I was a little late for this lecture.
This is how I made decisions.
Then are you saying
I should give up things
based on what I can and can't do?
Don't ask others how they do things. What
ultimately is the problem you're facing?
Tell me and I'll answer.
My problem?
(Sunim) Why are you
beating around the bush?
I'm telling you already.
(Sunim) What is your problem?
I don't know how I should live.
(Sunim) Tell me specifically.
I have no dreams anymore.
Not having a dream is a good thing.
(Questioner) Is it?
It is. Dreams are illusions, are they not?
We dream when we're asleep.
I rather have issues with
dreaming while sleeping.
What's wrong with not having a dream?
(Questioner) Without a dream,
(Questioner) I feel like my body exists
but my mind and soul doesn't.
That itself is a useless thought.
You do have body, mind and soul.
You just don't feel like you do.
(Questioner) My life seems
purposeless without a dream.
(Questioner) I feel heavy-hearted and lost
as this continues, hence I'm asking you.
Some people suffer from
having too many dreams.
How nice is it that
you don't have to make
choices among dreams?
It's not a bad thing, there is good to it.
Did you have breakfast?
(Questioner) I didn't.
What about lunch?
(Questioner) I did.
Dinner?
So you had two meals today?
Then it's all good.
You have no problem surviving.
I see.
(Sunim) Ask me anything.
(Audience Laughter)
What should I ask?
(Questioner Laugher)
If you don't have anything else, then don't.
(Questioner) Okay.
(Applause)
People back in the days would also worry
over similarly non-significant things.
Zen riddles talk of someone rambling
on and on saying Buddha this Buddha that.
To this a Zen master simply said,
"Why don't you just have a cup of tea?"
Do you get it?
So I'm asking you.
Why worry over something insignificant?
"Have you eaten?" "Yes."
"Then you're good."
In North Korea,
there are many starving to death.
You're creating useless thoughts.
If you have something you want to do,
just do it. If you don't...
Do you work or not?
(Questioner) I quit my job last August.
What are you doing now?
(Questioner) I'm taking a break.
That's why you're having useless thoughts.
(Audience Laughter)
If you're working, wouldn't you be
busy getting to work in the morning
whether
you're in a daze or not?
(Questioner) I'd be busy.
(Sunim) You would be busy
with the work that's given.
You'd be tired at night,
you'd fall asleep.
There is no problem here.
You're only deep in your thoughts
as you aren't doing anything.
Before you leave, ask a volunteer
about the Munkyung retreat center.
They have an Awakening retreat.
You should attend.
Once you do, you'll be able to
observe who you really are.
The you'll contemplate less about it.
If you don't have much to do, come join
our Jungto society. I'll keep you busy.
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) Okay.
(Sunim) You should be
doing something.
(Questioner) Yes.